Mss.Ms.Coll.96
American Philosophical Society
James V. Neel, papers, ca. 1939-1999
Circa 1939-1999
Mss.Ms.Coll.96
American Philosophical Society
112.0 Linear feet
The James V. Neel Papers document nearly every phase of the career of one of the founders of human population genetics in the United States. Neel was particularly thorough and organized, and retained virtually all of his significant scientific correspondence, committee reports, minutes of meetings, and drafts of manuscripts. The collection also includes data collected during Neel’s work among the Xavante, Yanomanö and other Indians. In a career that spanned the period from the late work of Thomas Hunt Morgan and Charles B. Davenport to the contemporary world of molecular genetics and nucleic-acids, Neel knew, worked with, and corresponded with many of the most influential 20th century practitioners of genetics. The collection begins in earnest in 1943, after Neel had decided to focus on human genetics. As a result, Neel’s work with Drosophila and none of his Drosophila manuscripts were preserved.
100 linear feet.
Demerec, M., (Milislav), 1895-1966
Dobzhansky, Theodosius Grigorievich, 1900-1975
Dunn, L. C., (Leslie Clarence), 1893-1974
Neel, James V., (James Van Gundia), 1915-2000
Stern, Curt, 1902-1981
Box 1-300
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Gift of James V. Neel, 1999.
Scope and Contents note
Native American Images note: 140 black and white silver gelatin photographs, photomechanical prints, pencil sketches, and maps of Yanomamo and Xavante Indians of Venezuela and Brazil collected by Neel during his fieldwork from 1962-1968. Primarily photographs by anthropologist Napoleon Chagnon of Yanomamo Indians while Neel studied chromosome aberrations and administered vaccinations. Both tribes depicted in jungle settlements with images of dwelling, weapons, farming, cooking, and dancing in native dress. Also, maps showing distribution of dialects. In Series VIIa Research notes and manuscripts—Amerindians.
Conditions Governing Access note
Papers of James V. Neel, pioneering human population geneticist and professor in the Department of Human Genetics, University of Michigan Medical School. Curt Stern's first graduate student at the University of Rochester, and a post-doctoral student under Theodosius Dobzhansky, Neel began his career as a Drosophila geneticist, but after taking his first professional appointment as an assistant professor at Dartmouth, decided to alter his course into human genetics. Reasoning that he needed a solid medical education to complement his genetical training, he returned to Rochester in 1942 to study for an MD.
Like all medical students during the Second World War, Neel was inducted into military service. Rochester was the base for studies in radiation biology associated with the Manhattan Project, and at the end of the war, with Neel still in the military, a chance friendship with the adjutant to the head of the project resulted in Neel's appointment to help organize a genetical survey of the atomic bomb survivors. In 1946-1947, Neel lived in Hiroshima, organizing this project, part of the Atomic Bomb Casualty Committee (ABCC), and he maintained a close connection to the study until his death. His work in Japan mushroomed, too, into a series of related projects into the biology and genetics of consanguinity, among other topics.
While at Rochester, Neel also began to establish a name for himself in other areas of human genetics. As a resident at Rochester's Strong Memorial Hospital, Neel encountered a case of thalassemia, and reading the medical literature, he became convinced that it was a genetic recessive disease. Over a span of five years, he delineated the genetic basis of haemoglobin diseases - first thalassemia, then sickle cell disease - in the process, helping to precipitate the revolution in biochemical genetics of the 1950s through 1970s. Neel's work also encompassed the evolutionary implications for these diseases, implanting balanced polymorphism and heterozygote advantage into the vocabularies of evolutionary biologists. Neel's studies of thalassemia and sickle cell disease were recognized with the receipt of the Lasker Award in 1955.
In the late 1950s, Neel entered into a third major set of projects, turning to extensive field studies in population genetics. Recognizing that the number of human populations isolated from modern medicines and modern technology was rapidly dwindling, Neel embarked on an ambitious genetic survey of the comparatively "primitive" Xavante of Brazil and, later, the Yanomamo of the Brazilian-Venezuelan borderlands. These studies, carried out over the course of more than a decade, and involving even longer spans of laboratory work, constitute the first and most comprehensive studies of human population and breeding structure and genetic diseases among "primitive" peoples. Dr. Neel died in February, 2000.
General note
Neel’s autobiography, Physician to the Gene Pool (Wiley: New York, 1994), is an invaluable summary of his career and research interests.
Genetics Note
This collection contains materials which relate to the history of genetics.
American Eugenics Society Correspondence (42 items) 1953-1976
American Journal of Human Genetics Records (4 folders) 1967-1998
American Society of Human Genetics Records (18 items) 1969-1985
Beadle, George Wells Correspondence (20 items) 1949-1963
Beutler, Ernest Correspondence (26 items) 1956-2000
Carson, Hampton L. Correspondence (10 items) 1956-1983
Caspari, Ernst Wilhelm Correspondence (33 items) 1951-1985
Demerec, Milislav Correspondence (9 items) 1949-1950
Dobzhansky, Theodosius Correspondence (63 items) 1946-1971
Dunn, Leslie Clarence Correspondence (52 items) 1951-1971
Ephrussi, Boris Correspondence (12 items) 1942, 1962
Glass, Bentley Correspondence (38 items) 1948-1982
Goldschmidt, Richard Benedict Correspondence (6 items) 1952
Hollaender, Alexander Correspondence (2 folders) 1948-1985
Hare, George Harrison; Amerindians; Atmospheric radiation.; Consanguinity; Correspondence.; Drafts (preliminary versions).; Environmental health.; Gelatin silver prints; Genetics--Research; Hematology; Heredity; Human population genetics.; Indians of South America--Brazil; Indians of South America--Venezuela; Lectures; Maps.; Photomechanical prints; Sketches.; Xavante Indians; Yanomamo Indians
- Selected Inventory from Genetics Subject Guide
  - American Eugenics Society, 1953-1976; Correspondence ( 42 items )
    American Eugenics Society; Atomic Bomb Casualty Commission; Conferences and symposia; Eugenics; Evolution; Human genetics; International Congress of Genetics; Population genetics; Publication; Radiation genetics; Requests for reprints
  - American Journal of Human Genetics, 1967-1998; Records ( 4 folders )
    American Society of Human Genetics; Eugenics; Evolution; Fellowships, assistantships; Human genetics; Molecular genetics; Population genetics; Publication -- American Journal of Human Genetics; Radiation genetics; Referee's report; Reviews; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.
  - American Society of Human Genetics, 1969-1985; Records ( 18 items )
    American Society of Human Genetics; Business; Cancer, chemotherapy; Human genetics; International Congress of Human Genetics -- Third Congress; Population genetics; Publication; Radiation genetics; Scientific organizations, meetings, programs; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.
  - Beadle, George Wells, 1949-1963; Correspondence ( 20 items )
    California Institute of Technology; Congratulations, greetings, thanks -- Kimber Award; Fellowships, assistantships; Graduate study; Honors -- Kimber Award; Human genetics; Lectures, public speaking; Muller, Hermann Joseph; National Academy of Sciences; Population genetics; Publication; Radiation genetics; Travel -- Invitations, arrangements; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.
  - Beutler, Ernest, 1956-2000; Correspondence ( 26 items )
    Cancer, chemotherapy; Editorial matters -- Blood Cells, Molecules, and Diseases; Human genetics; Medical research; Molecular genetics; Publication -- Blood Cells, Molecules, and Diseases
  - Carson, Hampton L., 1956-1983; Correspondence ( 10 items )
    Conferences and symposia; Genetics of plants; Population genetics; Recommendations; Stalker, Harrison Dailey; Stern, Curt; Travel -- Invitations, arrangements
  - Caspari, Ernst Wilhelm, 1951-1985; Correspondence ( 33 items )
    Beadle, George Wells; Biographical and personal data; Biographical and personal data -- Hadorn,; Biographical and personal data -- Stern, Curt; Conferences and symposia; Congratulations, greetings, thanks -- National Academy of Sciences; Educational matters -- Germany; History of biology, especially genetics; Human genetics; International Congress of Genetics -- Tenth Congress; Invitations; Molecular genetics; Photographs; Publication -- Genetics; Radiation genetics; Requests for reprints; University of Rochester; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.; Willier, Benjamin Harrison; World War I -- Germany
  - Demerec, Milislav, 1949-1950; Correspondence ( 9 items )
    Anthropology; Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory; Conferences and symposia; Evolution; Human genetics; Population genetics; Travel -- Invitations, arrangements
  - Dobzhansky, Theodosius, 1946-1971; Correspondence ( 63 items )
    American Eugenics Society; Biographical and personal data; Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory; Conferences and symposia; Congratulations, greetings, thanks -- Dobzhansky, Theodosius. 70th birthday; Congratulations, greetings, thanks -- National Academy of Sciences; Crow, James F.; Dunn, Leslie Clarence; Evolution; Human genetics; Human genetics -- Race; International Congress of Genetics; Invitations; Kimura, Motoo; Lectures, public speaking; Lectures, public speaking -- Rockefeller University; Li, Ching Chun; Medical research; National Institutes of Health; National Research Council; Population genetics; Publication; Radiation genetics; Russian politics and science; Shull, George Harrison; Statistics, biostatistics, biometrics; Travel -- Invitations, arrangements; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc. -- The Changing Man; World War II -- Impact on science
  - Dunn, Leslie Clarence, 1951-1971; Correspondence ( 52 items )
    American Philosophical Society; American Society of Human Genetics; Conferences and symposia; Evolution; History of biology, especially genetics; Human genetics; Invitations; Lectures, public speaking; Population genetics; Preservation of historical materials; Publication; Recommendations; Research support; Scientific organizations, meetings, programs -- Institute for the Study of Human Variation; Solicitations for support or contribution; Teaching -- Columbia University
  - Ephrussi, Boris, 1942, 1962; Correspondence ( 12 items )
    Anthropology; Human genetics; Lectures, public speaking; Levi-Strauss, Claude; Molecular genetics; Publication; Travel -- Invitations, arrangements
  - Glass, Bentley, 1948-1982; Correspondence ( 38 items )
    American Philosophical Society; American Society of Human Genetics; Atomic Bomb Casualty Commission; Biographical and personal data -- Stern, Curt; Conferences and symposia; Drosophila genetics; History of biology, especially genetics; Human genetics; Invitations; Li, Ching Chun; Population genetics; Preservation of historical materials; Publication -- American Naturalist; Publication -- Quarterly Review of Biology; Radiation genetics; Reviews; Statistics, biostatistics, biometrics
  - Goldschmidt, Richard Benedict, 1952; Correspondence ( 6 items )
    Behavioral genetics, IQ; Human genetics
  - Hollaender, Alexander, 1948-1985; Correspondence ( 2 folders )
    Atomic Bomb Casualty Commission; Atomic Energy Commission; Biochemistry and organic chemistry; Biographical and personal data; Cancer, chemotherapy; Conferences and symposia; Cytogenetics; Embryology, developmental genetics; Human genetics; Invitations; Medical research; Mouse genetics; Oak Ridge National Laboratory; Political issues -- Environment; Political issues -- Pollution; Population genetics; Radiation genetics; Recommendations; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.
- Graphics
  - Preparing for Yanomamo ceremony, 1967
  - Xavante boy vaccinated, 1964
  - Xavante boys, 1964
  - Xavante woman with children, 1964
  - Yanomamo boy, 1967
  - Yanomamo dance, 1967
  - Yanomamo men with James V. Neel, 1967
  - Yanomamo war dance, 1967